[Music]
this appeal concerns the tax treatment
between 1990 and 2009 of UK companies
which receive dividends from share
holdings and overseas companies it
raises a number of technical issues of
tax law and also an issue in the law of
unjust enrichment which is of wider
importance at that time a UK company
which received dividends from another UK
company was exempt from corporation tax
on that income and received a tax credit
equal to the amount of advanced
corporation tax or a CT but the
distributing company had paid on the
distribution the dividend together with
the tax credit constituted what was
called franked investment income in the
hands of the recipient company which it
could use to reduce its own liability to
a CT on distributions to its own
shareholders in contrast a UK company
which receive dividends from an overseas
company was subject to corporation tax
on that income forevermore it did not
receive a tax credit on the dividends
this situation was was contrary to EU
law because it discriminated against
companies which invested in countries
outside the UK Prudential brought this
claim against the revenue to recover
corporation tax and a CT which had been
levied contrary to EU law it is common
ground the Prudential is entitled to an
appropriate tax credit and to repayment
of any tax unlawfully charged the
current dispute concerns the amount to
be awarded the first issue which arises
in the appeal is whether EU law requires
the tax credit to be set by reference to
the overseas tax actually paid as a
revenue submit or by reference to
foreign nominal tax rate asked to say
the headline rate before account has
taken of exemptions and reliefs as
Prudential submits the Supreme Court
dismisses the revenues appeal on this
issue the judgments of European Court of
Justice established but the credit for
foreign dividends should be calculated
by reference to the foreign nominal tax
rate there is no suggestion in the
European case law that any distinction
should be drawn in this respect between
portfolio holdings such as Prudential
held as to say holdings of less than 10%
of a company's shares and non portfolio
holdings as a revenue had argued the
second issue and the one of wider
importance is whether Prudential is
entitled to compound interest on tax
which was levied in breach of EU law on
the basis that revenue were unjustly
enriched by the opportunity to use the
money in question or on the other hand
are only entitled to simple interest
such as would be paid on any unpaid debt
this might seem to be a rather technical
point but millions of pounds turn on the
answer in fact billions of pounds turn
on the answer the Supreme Court allows
the revenues appeal on this issue in the
2007 case of Sempra metals or a similar
question arose a majority of the House
of Lords held that a claim would line
unjust enrichment for restitution of
compound interest on money which was
paid prematurely as a consequence of a
mistake a number of developments since
that decision indicate that it failed to
have regard to some relevant provisions
of tax legislation created problems in
the law of limitation which governs the
time within which claims must be brought
to court and caused disruption in public
finances it's also inconsistent with the
recent decision of this court in the
case of investment trusts companies
which explained the requirement for
there to be a defective transfer of
value by the claimant and to the
defendant if a claim based on unjust
enrichment is to lie
the recipients possession of money
mistakenly paid to him and his
consequent opportunity to use it is not
a distinct transfer of value additional
to the transfer constituted by the
payment of the money itself accordingly
there is no right to interest on the
basis of unjust enrichment the Supreme
Court fir 4 departs and the reasoning in
Sempra metals on this issue and rejects
Prudential's claims to compound interest
except insofar as they were accepted by
the Revenue the third issue is whether a
claim lies in restitution to recover
lawful a CT which was set against
unlawful corporation tax the Supreme
Court allows the revenues appeal on this
issue where a lawful a CT was set
against unlawful corporation tax the
revenue did not receive unlawfully
levied tax as required for a claim under
EU law if an apparent charged
corporation tax was unlawful that charge
was a nullity the lawful AC T could not
have been set against finality but would
remain available to be utilized
furthermore the payment of the AC T did
not entail a defective transfer of value
which failed to be corrected as required
by the investment Trust Company's case
the next issue is whether if a CT from a
pool which includes both unlawful and
lawful a CT is utilized against an
unlawful charge to corporation tax the
unlawful AC T should be regarded as a
prepayment of the unlawful corporation
tax liability or as partly lawful and
partly unlawful pro-rata the Supreme
Court allows credentials cross-appeal on
this issue unlawful AC t is treated as
set first against unlawful corporation
tax since unlawful corporation tax is a
nullity that means that the unlawful AC
t is recoverable unless it's been set
against a lawful charge to corporation
tax the final issue is whether we're a
francs investment income
was carried back to an earlier quarter
it should be treated as having been
applied to relieve the lawful and
unlawful AC t pro rata or only lawful AC
T the Supreme Court allows Prudential's
cross-appeal on this issue franked
investment income which is carried back
to an earlier quarter is to be regarded
as having been applied to relieve only
lawful AC t the revenues pro rata
approach would have the effect of
depriving a company of the tax credit at
the foreign nominal tax rate which is
required under EU law
you